# Wil Thomason

804.591.7318 Cornell University Contact Department of Computer Science wbthomason@cs.cornell.edu Information

343 Campus Road Ithaca, NY 14853

https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~wil/

OBJECTIVE

I am broadly interested in algorithms for robotics, with a focus on planning algorithms and integrated task and motion planning. My work studies efficient, principled approaches to solving realistic robot problems with both logical and geometric complexity. I am also interested in fusing classical planning methods with machine learning to enable more robust, capable robots, as well as algorithms for efficient planning in constrained domains, programming languages research, and robot autonomy/decision-making. In all my work, I care about finding solutions that are both soundly based in theory and practical for real-world use.

Research Interests Robotics: integrated task and motion planning, constrained planning, multi-agent coordination

Machine Learning: learning to plan, combining ML with classical planning

**Programming Languages:** type theory, effect systems, compilers

**EDUCATION** 

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY Ph.D., Computer Science

June 2019 – Present

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

August 2015 - June 2019

MS, Computer Science

Relevant Courses: CS 6820: Advanced Algorithms (Fall 2015), CS 6786: Advanced Machine Learning (Spring 2016), CS 6110: Advanced Programming Languages (Spring 2016), MAE 6790: Intelligent Sensor Planning and Control (Fall 2016), CS 6751: Intro to Mobile Manipulation (Spring 2017), MAE 6770: Formal Methods for Robotics (Fall 2017)

University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA

August 2012 - May 2015

BS, Computer Science, Mathematics

Relevant Courses: CS 6161: Graduate Design and Analysis of Algorithms (Fall 2014), CS 6610: Graduate Programming Languages (Fall 2014)

**PUBLICATIONS** 

# Automatic Distributed Multi-Agent Coordination of Single-Agent Robot Controllers. ICRA (in submission) (2019)

Wil Thomason, Abhishek Anand, Greg Morrisett, Ross Knepper.

We present a framework for automatically transforming single-agent robot controllers into distributed multi-agent controllers with guaranteed safety and progress under lightweight assumptions. The core of this framework is a simple protocol that maintains two invariants: (a) all executed actions are non-colliding, and (b) there is always a valid plan to reverse the system back to an earlier state.

# A Unified Sampling-Based Approach to Integrated Task and Motion Planning. ISRR (2019)

Wil Thomason, Ross Knepper.

We contribute a novel approach to integrated task and motion planning that adapts any off-the-shelf motion planning algorithm to automatically solve task and motion planning problems. We construct a state space embedding the full symbolic and continuous state of a planning problem into a single highly factorable space. Combined with a continuous semantics for Boolean predicates, which we use to derive navigation functions to task-level salient regions of the continuous space, we can efficiently solve complex manipulation problems with few domain-specific assumptions.

# Social Momentum: A Framework for Legible Navigation in Dynamic Multi-Agent Environments. HRI (2018)

Christoforos Mavrogiannis, Wil Thomason, Ross Knepper.

We design a planning framework that aims at generating motion that clearly communicates an agent's intended collision avoidance strategy rather than its destination. Our framework estimates the most likely intended avoidance protocols of others based on their past behaviors, superimposes them, and generates an expressive and socially compliant robot action that reinforces the expectations of others regarding these avoidance protocols.

# Zero-Shot Learning for Unfamiliar Gesture Recognition. ISER (2016)

Wil Thomason, Ross Knepper.

We explore a method for achieving increased understanding of complex, situated communications by leveraging coordinated natural language, gesture, and context. These three problems have largely been treated separately, but unified consideration of them can yield gains in comprehension.

## An Accurate Real-Time RFID-Based Location System. IJRFITA (2016)

Kirti Chawla, Christopher McFarland, Gabriel Robins, Wil Thomason.

We outline an RFID-based object localization framework addressing challenges of performance and applicability and propose the use of Received Signal Strength (RSS) to model the behavior of radio signals decaying over distance in an orientationagnostic manner to simultaneously locate a number of stationary and mobile objects.

# **Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award**

Cornell University Department of Computer Science, May of 2017

Awarded for my work as a TA for the new Foundations of Robotics course in Fall 2016, taught by Ross Knepper.

NDSEG Fellow American Society for Engineering Education, April of 2017 The National Defense Science and Engineering Graduate (NDSEG) Fellowship is a highly competitive, portable fellowship that is awarded to U.S. citizens and nationals who intend to pursue a doctoral degree in one of fifteen supported disciplines. NDSEG confers high honors upon its recipients, and allows them to attend whichever U.S. institution they choose. (https://ndseg.asee.org/)

NSF GRFP Fellow The National Science Foundation, March of 2017 The NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program recognizes and supports outstanding graduate students in NSF-supported science, technology, engineering, and mathematics disciplines who are pursuing research-based Master's and doctoral degrees at accredited United States institutions. (https://www.nsfgrfp.org/)

#### **Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award**

Cornell University Department of Computer Science, May of 2016 Awarded for my work as a TA for the Intro to Python course (CS 1110) in Fall 2015, taught by Walker White.

NSF GRFP Honorable Mention The National Science Foundation, March of 2016

AWARDS

The NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program recognizes and supports outstanding graduate students in NSF-supported science, technology, engineering, and mathematics disciplines who are pursuing research-based Master's and doctoral degrees at accredited United States institutions.(https://www.nsfgrfp.org/)

# Louis T. Rader Outstanding Education Undergraduate Student Award University of Virginia Department of Computer Science, May of 2015

Awarded for my work for several years as a TA for multiple courses in the computer science department at UVA.

#### Presentations

"A Flexible Sampling-Based Approach to Task and Motion Planning."

RSS 2019 Workshop on Robust Task and Motion Planning

http://dyalab.mines.edu/2019/rss-workshop/thomason.pdf

June 23, 2019

"Which comes first, the task plan or the motion plan?." (joint with Ross Knepper) RSS 2018 Workshop on Exhibition and Benchmarking of Task and Motion Planners June 30, 2018

http://www.neil.dantam.name/2018/rss-tmp-workshop/

"Exploiting Heterogeneity in Robot Teams Through a Formalism of Capabilities."

RSS 2018 Workshop on Heterogeneity and Diversity for Resilience in Multi-Robot
Systems

July 15, 2017

https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~wil/papers/rss2017\_workshop\_heterogeneous\_coordination.pdf

"Toward Contextual Grounding of Unfamiliar Gestures for Human-Robot Interaction." FG 2017: First International Workshop on Adaptive Shot Learning for Gesture Understanding and Production May 30, 2017

https://www.cs.cornell.edu/~wil/papers/asl4gup2017\_unfamiliargestures.pdf

"Recognizing Unfamiliar Gestures for Human-Robot Interaction through Zero Shot Learning."

ISER 2016 October 6th, 2016

http://www.iser2016.org/program/

"Recognizing Unfamiliar Gestures for Human-Robot Interaction through Zero-Shot Learning."

 $2nd\ Workshop\ on\ Model\ Learning\ for\ Human-Robot\ Communication,\ RSS\ 2016$  June 19th, 2016

http://www.ece.rochester.edu/projects/rail/mlhrc2016/

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### Graduate Research Assistant

August 2015 - Present

Cornell University, Department of Computer Science

Advised by Professor Ross Knepper, I have studied problems in the domains of integrated task and motion planning, human-robot interaction and multi-agent planning. Specifically, I have made advances in efficient task and motion planning, gesture recognition, and coordination for ad hoc teams of heterogeneous robots. This work has resulted in several publications and presentations, and is ongoing.

#### Undergraduate Research Assistant

August 2014 – July 2015

The University of Virginia, Department of Computer Science

I worked with Professor Westley Weimer on automatic software functionality transplantation. We developed an algorithm based on analyzing differences in test suite performance to identify software modules responsible for specific functionality and a combination of function dependency tracing and extraction with the GenProg program repair tool to perform transplants.

### Undergraduate Research Assistant

January 2013 – May 2014

The University of Virginia, Department of Computer Science

As a part of Professor Gabriel Robins' lab, I helped to create an efficient, scalable system for real-time localization of objects in 3D space using passive RFID tags. In addition to designing and running experiments for the system, I researched and created a novel approach to distinguishing between noisy measurements and measurements corresponding to moving objects. This approach, which was based on a sliding-window particle filter, significantly increased the accuracy of our system. This work resulted in a journal publication.

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

## Graduate Teaching Assistant: CS 4750

Fall 2016 & Fall 2017

Cornell University

TA for Foundations of Robotics: A new course designed to introduce students to the knowledge they need to conduct research in robotics. I helped to create the course syllabus, textbook, and software for course assignments, and was also responsible for giving weekly office hours, grading, and assisting with lecturing.

# Graduate Teaching Assistant: CS 1110

Fall 2015

Cornell University

Head TA for Cornell's introductory computer science course. Responsible for coordinating TA staff, giving review lectures, supervising lab sessions, grading, and giving weekly office hours.

# Instructor: Introduction to Robotics

Spring 2015

University of Virginia

I designed and taught a 1-credit course introducing undergraduate students to core topics in robotics. As a part of the course, students built and programmed their own quadrotor robots and learned about basic kinematics, control, perception, and learning.

### Undergraduate Teaching Assistant: CS 4610

Spring 2015

University of Virginia

TA for UVA's undergraduate programming languages course.

#### Undergraduate Teaching Assistant: CS 4710

Spring 2015

University of Virginia

TA for UVA's undergraduate artificial intelligence course.

# Undergraduate Teaching Assistant: CS 4414

Spring 2014

University of Virginia

TA for UVA's undergraduate operating systems course. Helped create course content using the Rust programming language as well as an automatic grading server for the class.

#### Undergraduate Teaching Assistant: CS 2150

Fall 2013 – Spring 2015

University of Virginia

TA for UVA's undergraduate data structures and C++ programming course.

### Industry Experience

# Software Engineering Intern at Fluencia

May 2015 - August 2015

Worked on adding voice understanding for speech practice exercises

- Improved voice understanding software
- Integrated into language learning website
- Created test and development framework for voice exercises

## Software Development Engineer Intern at Microsoft May 2014 – August 2014 Microsoft Accounts Client Team

- Implemented and tested cryptographic operations and network protocol for forthcoming feature in Microsoft Accounts Android app. The implemented feature enables more convenient and more secure sign-in for Microsoft accounts via mobile devices.
- Coordinated the work of several other interns working on related components
  of the same project to ensure successful integration and delivery of the fullyfunctional feature ahead of schedule.

# **Software Development Engineer Intern at Microsoft** May 2013 – August 2013 Xbox LIVE Cloud Security Team

- Designed, implemented, and shipped a RESTful web service capable of logging and auditing security records in Xbox LIVE in real time. Also designed, created, and tuned associated database and procedures. Service is currently in use in the Xbox LIVE network.
- Spearheaded and completed a total rewrite of an important development library starting with old, cobbled together library used across principal components of the Xbox LIVE network, redesigned and reimplemented the entire library to provide a faster and easier to use interface to the same core functionality.

TECHNICAL SKILLS **Programming Languages:** C++, Python, Rust, C, CL, Haskell, OCaml, etc. **Technologies:** Linux, ROS, OMPL, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Git, CUDA, etc.

Languages

English (Fluency: Native speaker) German (Fluency: Working)

#### OUTREACH

#### **Expanding Your Horizons**

Spring 2016 – Spring 2019

Taught middle school girls from at-risk communities about programming https://www.eyh.cornell.edu/

- Created interface for introducing the concept of programming with state machines
- Wrote ROS software to run state machine code on a Kuka youBot

#### UVa High School Programming Contest

Spring 2014 – Spring 2015

Helped plan and run the biggest programming competition for high school students in the mid-Atlantic region.

http://acm.cs.virginia.edu/hspc.php

- Created contest problems
- Planned contest logistics
- Helped run contest

### UVa CS Education Week

Winter 2014 - Winter 2015

Visited area schools to teach workshops on introductory programming with JKarel